Papers of Bernice Cosulich "1923-1956"
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Bernice Cosulich 1923-1956
AZ 283
Cosulich, Bernice, 1896-1956
Papers of Bernice Cosulich consists of correspondence, published and unpublished articles, clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, and notes related to Cosulich’s work writing for the Arizona Daily Star newspaper and various magazines, her book Tucson, and future projects including a projected biography of actress Helena Modjeska and a work on Arizona’s ghost towns, dating between 1923 and 1956.
12 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://www.library.arizona.edu/speccoll
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Journalist and author, Tucson, Arizona; Bernice Cosulich was born in Iowa in 1896. She married Gilbert Cosulich in 1916 and they had one daughter. Ms. Cosulich was on the staff of the Arizona Daily Star newspaper from 1922 to 1948. She also worked as a special correspondent for the New York Times, and Life, Time and Fortune magazines and her work was published in many other magazines. She worked as the social editor from 1922 to 1929 and interviewed famous visitors to Arizona. Later she covered the state legislature from 1941 to 1946, and participated in a study of the Colorado River which led to the 1944 Colorado River Compact concerning water allocations. Her book, entitled Tucson, contains stories of pioneers and historic sites.
Arrangement
This Collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Personal material, correspondence, notes, unpublished materials, 1922-1953
Series II: Published articles (by Cosulich and other authors, with accompanying correspondence), 1927-1953
Series III: Ghost towns, Tucson, Tubac (miscellaneous research material).
Series IV: Helena Modjeska research material.
Series V: Scrapbooks,(news articles and photographs by BC) 1923-1954
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, notes, clippings, photographs, typescripts, and publications relating chiefly to her career with the Arizona Daily Star and as a freelance writer. Material, chiefly articles and newspaper clippings, concerns local and statewide subjects, including Indians, mining operations, and desert plants for medicinal purposes; also letters from various American and English authors, notes for a projected biography of actress Helena Modjeska, and notes and snapshots for a projected work on Arizona ghost towns. Also present are published and unpublished articles about John Galsworthy, Lewis W. Douglas, and Harold Bell Wright. Correspondents include George Doran, Oliver St. John Gogarty, and Frances Gillmor. There are photographs of Morenci, Arizona mining operations; excavations at Ventana Cave, Tucson; the 1946 building of Davis Dam on the Colorado River; and the 1946 Point of Pines, University of Arizona Field Archaeology School. A detailed index to newspaper clippings in the scrapbooks is present.
Cosulich, Bernice--Archives; Doran, George H. (George Henry)--1869-1956; Galsworthy, John, 1867-1933; Douglas, Lewis W. (Lewis Williams), 1894-; Gillmor, Frances, 1903-; Gogarty, Olivers St. John, 1878-1957; Modjeska, Helena, 1840-1909; Wright, Harold Bell, 1872-1944; University of Arizona--History; Arizona daily star; Authors, American--Correspondence; Medicinal plants--Southwestern States; Extinct cities--Arizona; Ghost towns--Arizona; Copper mines and mining--Arizona; Mines and mineral resources--Arizona; Pioneers--Arizona; Women journalists--Arizona; Tucson (Ariz.)--History; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico)--Water rights--Arizona; Mexico--Description and travel; Tucson (Ariz.)--Social life and customs; Tubac (Ariz.)--History; Arizona--History, Local; Tombstone (Ariz.)--History; Morenci (Ariz.)--History; Arizona--Description and travel; Arizona--Politics and government
Container List
- Series I: Personal material, correspondence, notes, unpublished manuscripts, 1922-1953
  Consists chiefly of responses to interview requests, requests for Cosulich to review books, and comments on published interviews. Some are friends and acquaintances of Cosulich. Many are writing from local guest ranches where they were staying. This series is arranged by correspondent or topic.
  - Miscellaneous personal material (photographs of Cosulich, clippings, inscribed fly-leaves from books given to B.C., letters regarding her illness,), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Professional, personal, condolence) (A-E) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aero Corporation of California, (1929)
    - American Press Institute and William R. Mathews, 1946
    - Anderson, Sherwood (postcard), 1936
    - Andrews, Roy Chapman, 1948, 1953
    - Astor, Lord (includes photograph), 1948, 1953
    - Baker, Ray Stannard, 1932, 1942
    - Birney, Hoffman, 1931
    - Bolton, Herbert, 1936
    - Chaliapin, Feodor, 1926
    - Collins, Joseph, 1946
    - Coolidge, Mary Roberts, 1934
    - Cooper, Dr. Frederic T., 1931-1937
    - Croy, Homer, 1942-1943
    - Cummings, E. E.(includes regrets in form of brief poem), 1946
    - Curtis, Cyrus H. K., 1925
    - Dowdey, Clifford, undated
    - Dreiser, Theodore, 1936
  - Correspondence (F-Z) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Fergusson, Erna, 1935-1936,1948
    - Finney, Charles, 1936
    - Foreman, Grant, 1941
    - Gillmor, Frances, 1932-1935, 1940
    - Hanley, T. E., 1948
    - Haunz, Dr. Edward, 1946
    - Hawthorne, Hildegard, 1931-1935
    - Hughes, Charles E. to Fred Finney, 1942
    - Kidd, Rear Admiral I.C. of the U.S.S. Arizona, 1939
    - Kitt, Katherine, 1933
    - Lavender, Harrison M., 1948
    - Lewisohn, Ludwig, 1942
    - McCutcheon, John T., 1932
    - Mullett, Mary B., 1932-1933
    - Pegler, Westbrook, 1948
    - Petrova, Olga, undated
    - Pfeiffer, C. Leonard, 1948
    - Rak, Mary Kidder, 1945
    - Reed, W. Maxwell, 1946
    - Scully, Frank, 1935-1936
    - Sherwood, Robert, 1941
    - Stokes, Harold, 1938, 1940
    - Steele, Wilbur Daniel, 1933
    - Tarbell, Ida M., 1940
    - Taylor, Rosemary Drachman, 1943, 1948
    - TIME Magazine-telegram, 1947
    - Wiley, Louis,(, 1935
    - Williamson, Thames and Billiy, 1935
  - Correspondence - George H. Doran, 1935-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Oliver St. John Gogarty, 1933-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence – Right to work, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Medicinal plants (Notes, photos, seeds, etc.) Typed interviews and correspondence with Delphina and Sam Angelo at Sells, Arizona, about Tohono O'odham use of native plants for medicine, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mining operations at Morenci and Metcalf (Notes, photos, etc.) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Forest Service material (copies of Fred Winn's research) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Unpublished manuscripts: (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Secession and Seceders", 1922
  - "Indian Bells for Christmas: A Copper Story"
  - "The Rug"
- Series II: Published Articles (chiefly by Cosulich with accompanying correspondence), 1922-1953
  - Articles (about John Galsworthy), 1925-1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Draft of 1925 interview, published in Arizona Daily Star “Lifes Ironies Inspire John Galsworthy,” International Book Review, April 1926
  - "A Dumb but Grateful Diner—John Galsworthy.” Unpublished
  - John Galsworthy’s talk to Tucson Rotary Club
  - Articles about Harold Bell Wright, 1924-1927, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The Methods of Harold Bell Wright," The Editor, August 3, 1930
  - "Bad Things Don’t Pay," Success, July 1925
  - "Crumbs from the Table of Success," Writer’s Monthly, December 1925
  - "Harold Bell Wright Pays for Success," the Studebaker Wheel, July 1927
  - “Mr. Wright Builds a Boat,” Sunset, August 1927
  - “An Abode of Peace on the Painted Desert,” (Wright’s home),Sunset, September 1927
  - Letter, February 11, 1944
  - Articles Lewis W. Douglas, 1947, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - “Mr. Douglas of Arizona, friend of Cowboys and Kings,” Arizona Highways, September 1953
  - Articles “Making the ‘Old Bit’ Pay.”(prison libraries) New York Herald Tribune, Aug. 3, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Articles “Seeing Southern Arizona with Bernice Cosulich,” Arizona Daily Star(newspaper series), Spring 1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Articles (Arizona – local) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “The Newspaper Takes a Hand: A Successful Book Review Contest,” The Elementary English Review, October 1927
  - "The New Temple of Music and Art in Tucson," Progressive Arizona, December 1927
  - “Dudes on the Last Frontier,” New York Herald Tribune, January. 26, 1930
  - “Airing Arizona,” (photos only), Air Travel News. Proof of text: “The Land that God Forgot.” (not published), January 1930
  - “Arizona State Chapter Convention,” P.E.O. Record, June 1935
  - “Looking at Arizona,” Overland Trails, January 1936
  - “The Vulture, Henry Wickenburg’s Mine,” Arizona Highways, May 1942
  - “History of Flight” [mural at Davis-Monthan Field],Arizona Highways, May 1942
  - “Eighty Years of Growth in Tucson, 1903-1953:" The Southern Arizona Bank and Trust Company. 32-page booklet by Cosulich, undated
  - “Home of Hope” [Arizona Girls Ranch] American Soroptimist, November/December 1955
  - Various contributions to Sunset magazine:, November 1953, March 1954, Janurary 1955
  - Articles (Indians and Archaeology) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Review of “I Have Seen Them Dance,” published in a previous issue, The Literary Workshop,.1, no.3, [1934?]
  - “A Yaqui Passion Play in Arizona,” Travel, March 1931
  - “Past and Present Meet at Ventana Cave,” Arizona Highways, September 1941
  - “Christmas Eve at San Xavier,” Arizona Highways, December. 1941
  - Digging in Arizona,” Life, [Point of Pines], September. 9, 1946
  - Articles (Nature and Science) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - “Deer in Laboratory Yield Odd Discoveries,” Outdoor Life, November 1935
  - “Careful! … It’s a Porcupine,” Outdoor Life, May 1937
  - “Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument,” Tucson, June 1937
  - “Photometer for Measuring Light from Far Distant Stars” [at Steward Observatory, University of Arizona], Sky, August 1937
  - “The Colorado,” Life, [unsigned but BC doubtless supplied much of the information on this], October. 23, 1944
  - Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum [Tucson] Brochure (unsigned), [1950]
  - Articles-People (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - “Wives of Public Utility Men Remind Us,” by E. C. Deal, Pres., People’s Light and Power Corp., Forbes, (Ghosted by Cosulich), June 15, 1930
  - “Arizona History Makers,” Union Oil Bulletin,(unsigned), September 1938
  - “They Built a Home That Crowns a Desert Hill,” [Mr. and Mrs. William Graham Bell] Arizona Highways, Feburuary 1942
  - “Wilshaw – Presenting the Home of the Cowlinshaws in Santa Cruz,” and “Lee Brothers – Big Game Hunters,” Arizona Highways, November 1942
  - “Old Pueblo Authors and Artists,” Arizona Highways,(famous visitors and residents of Tucson), January 1944
  - “Lady Rancher” [Renee Donnet] Arizona Highways, April 1948
  - Articles (Misc.) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Operation Democracy: The Town Affiliation Program. [N.Y., 1952?] Brochure (unsigned)
  - “Future Riviera is at Guaymas,” Tucson, March 1936
  - Fortune. Issue devoted to the Western States. (B.C. supplied copy), Feburary 1945
- Series III: Ghost Towns, Tucson and Tubac research material
  Note: The folders marked “Ghost Towns” contain materials removed from their original notebooks, but they remain in the same sequence as arranged by B.C. topically by subject or personal name. These include places and people in southern Arizona.
  - “Ghost Towns” (Outline and miscellaneous material.) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - “Ghost Towns” (A – E) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - “Ghost Towns” (F) (includes Fort Bowie, Fort Grant) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - “Ghost Towns” (G – O) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - “Ghost Towns” (P) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - “Ghost Towns” (R) (includes Redington) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - “Ghost Towns” (S) includes San Simon Valley) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - “Ghost Towns” (T – Z) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - “Ghost Towns” (Chapter 4: Tubac) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - “Ghost Towns” (Tombstone) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Tucson (Correspondence, publicity, notes, etc.) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - “Notes for Tubac novel” (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Three Centuries of Tubac History,” Arizona Highways, Oct. 1942 (Accompanied by notes and reference material.) (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series IV:, Helena Modjeska research
  - Interviews, notes, translations of letters, etc. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ralph Modjeska (Article by B.C.: “Bridges that Led to Fame, New York Herald Tribune, Jan. 19, 1930, and accompanying correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 2 notebooks containing references, background material, notes, etc. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cook, Mabel (Collins), The Story of Helen Modjeska. 2nd edition. London, W. H. Allen and Co., 1885
  - Modjeska, Helena, Memories and Impressions of Helena Modjeska; an autobiography. N.Y., Macmillan, 1910
  - Personal materials (Box 5)
  - Estate papers, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Legal documents, 1916-1951 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper articles about death of Cosulich, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Autobiographical writings "Grandparents", user copy (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Autobiographical writings "Grandparents", original (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Autobiographical research material, 1940-1952 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Musical composition "Bernice" by Pacheco, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Biographical, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Master's thesis on Cosulich by M. Bantlin, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1920, 1950s, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Condolence letters, death of Cosulich, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Published article, "A Visit to the U.S.S. Arizona", 1959 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1943-1950, photocopies of articles (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1943-1950, photocopies of articles (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Unpublished "Border Bride" (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photographs - Portraits (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Photographs - Cosulich and family (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Photographs - Cosulich and friends (Includes Jane Rider) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Photographs - Publicity for "Tucson" book (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Photographs - Cosulich's house (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, Oversized - Portraits (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Series V: Scrapbooks, 1923-1954 (New clippings and photographs)
  Volumes 1-3 and part of Volume 4 were prepared by Bernice Cosulich; the remainder were prepared by Special Collections in 1958-1959. The index was also prepared at that time. Volume 9 is entirely photographs and is only partially included in the index.
  - 1923-1929, Includes photographs of aviation, 1928 (p.5), Harold Bell Wright (p.14); Ajo and Sells (p.23); Triangle T Dude Ranch (p.26); the O.K. Corral, 1929 (p.27, 30); and Circle Z Ranch (p.63). (Volume 1)
  - 1930-1934 (some 1925), Includes dispatches and telegrams to and from the New York Times relating to Cosulich's reporting on the Dillinger capture; articles about Margaret Sanger; coverage of Martha Breasted wedding. (Volume 2)
  - 1927-1935, Includes photographs of Chiricahua Mountain ranches and the grave of Johnny Ringo. Also photographs (8x10) of the scene of the discovery of June Robles, a kidnapped child (p.120-124). (Volume 3)
  - 1935-1936, Includes photographs of people and buildings on the Tohono O'odham reservation (p.12-13); Casa Grande ruins (p.24); Molybdenum mine (p.34); Apache homes (p.37); Willcox (p.39); Greaterville (p.43); Ruby (p.62); Tubac and Tumacacori (p.65); the Arizona State Prison (p.57); and Dane Coolidge (p.97). (Volume 4)
  - 1937-1942, Includes photographs of Old Tucson and the movie Arizona (p.73), and Ventana Cave excavations (p.115). (Volume 5)
  - 1943-1946, Includes photographs of Point of Pines excavations (p.116); and Davis Dam (p.106). (Volume 6)
  - 1947-1948, Includes photographs of Tohono O'odham (p.7); Alamos, Mexico (p.28); a Pasqua Yaqui ceremony, 1948 (p.32); and desert birds and trees (p.47, 49). (Volume 7)
  - 1954, Includes one photograph of Cosulich with friends. (Volume 8)
  - Photographs, 1923-1954; Highlights include musicians, authors, and actors including John Galsworthy, Harold Bell Wright, Helen Keller, Rosemary Drachman Taylor, Jeff Milton, and Lone Wolf. Places represented include San Xavier Mission, Tombstone (the OK Corral, stage coach, and Epitaph office), Ajo, Sabino Canyon dam, and Mexico.; There are also a few photographs by Dane Coolidge, images of filming of the movie "The Mine With the Iron Door" near Canada del Oro; a rodeo at Circle Z Ranch, 1931; gymkhana at Hacienda del Sol, 1932; and the Lee's Ferry Bridge dedication (Volume 9)